<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian wisdome, or The excellency fame and right meanes of true wisdome As it was briefly delivered in a sermon in St Maries Church in Oxford. Novemb: 11. 1638. By H. Tozer B. D. Fellow of Exeter Colledge.</title>
            <author>Tozer, Henry, 1602-1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13851</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121020</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856211</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856211</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21739</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13851)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21739)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1644:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian wisdome, or The excellency fame and right meanes of true wisdome As it was briefly delivered in a sermon in St Maries Church in Oxford. Novemb: 11. 1638. By H. Tozer B. D. Fellow of Exeter Colledge.</title>
                  <author>Tozer, Henry, 1602-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 107, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by L. Lichfield,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. 1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: The excellency of wisdome.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21739:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21739:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHRISTIAN <hi>WISDOME,</hi> OR THE EXCELLENCY FAME AND RIGHT MEANES OF TRVE WISDOME. As it was briefly delivered in a Sermon in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> MARIES Church in OXFORD. <hi>Novemb:</hi> 11. 1638. By H. TOZER B. D. Fellow of Exeter Colledge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by L. LICHFIELD <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1639.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21739:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21739:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE</hi> R. HONOVRABLE LORD <hi>ROBERT</hi> EARLE OF ANCRAM.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>R. HONOVRABLE.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> HERE adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to preſent to your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>of the Praiſe and Worth of Wiſdome.</hi> Were the Diſcourſe anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Subject, it were
<pb facs="tcp:21739:3"/> a Treaſure indeed and well worth the keeping, but the emptineſſe of that may well giue the World juſt cauſe to think it to be, as it is, too far below the acceptance of ſo great a Perſonage, and my ſelfe ſo much the more unadviſedly bold in preſenting the ſame unto You. However, it will not bee very ſeaſonable to enlarge a Preface with variety of ſtudied words and elaborate expreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:21739:3"/> for the obtaining of Your <hi>Lordſhip's</hi> favora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acceptation, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed to adventure on a ſecond incongruous boldneſſe in treſpaſsing on Your wonted <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and dayly ſerious <hi>Imployment:</hi> whereof the One, as the world knows well, reſpecteth not ſo much a verball obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance as plaine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty and Truth; and the Other, which duly is diſcharged in waiting on
<pb facs="tcp:21739:4"/> the ſervice of GOD and Your KING, doth ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome give leave to ſpend much time in the reading of long Epiſtles and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Dedications.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, to ſay all that is needfull in a litle, if any by reading this plaine Diſcourſe ſhall be occaſioned to entertaine one Thought of ſeeking after VViſdome more than before hee had, 'tis that which, God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, was my ayme in the
<pb facs="tcp:21739:4"/> Publication thereof: and if, for this purpoſe, Your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> ſhall pleaſe to let it goe forth under Your Honourable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and accept the Dedication of it as a true acknowledgment of that ſervice, wherein I have ſtood long engaged, 'tis more than I deſerve, and all that I doe or can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</p>
            <p>God direct the hearts of all men to ſeek after that wiſdome, which is
<pb facs="tcp:21739:5"/> acceptable and makes them ſuch, who love it: and may the Gift there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of be ever multiplied on Your Honourable Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to the magnifying of God's glory here, and Your's hereafter: which is the true deſire and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayned Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Humble Servant <hi>HENRY TOZER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21739:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHRISTIAN</hi> VVISDOME, <hi>OR</hi> THE EXCELLENCY, FAME, AND RIGHT meanes of <hi>TRVE WIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOME, Delivered on</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>1. KINGS: 10.24.</bibl>
                  <p>All the earth ſought unto <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> to heare his wiſdome which God had put in his heart.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was once the gracious bounty of <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> when he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to him in <hi>Gibeon,</hi> to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21739:6"/> bid him ask of him what he would. <hi>Aske,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>what J ſhall give thee.</hi> 1. King. 3.5.<note place="margin">1. Kin. 3.5.</note> Had <hi>Solomon</hi> been a riot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Libertine,</hi> he would (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this unlimited proffer) have asked <hi>Length of daies;</hi> that ſo he might have enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the pleaſures of ſin for a <hi>long ſeaſon;</hi> or had he been a covetous <hi>worldling,</hi> he would have asked <hi>Riches</hi> for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; that ſo, having enough laid up for many yeares, hee might have ſung a <hi>Requiem</hi> to his ſoul, bidding her eat, drink, and bee merry with that, which hee never took paines to get, but had it for the <hi>asking;</hi> or, had he been a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21739:6"/> 
               <hi>Cruell</hi> man, one of thoſe <hi>Wolves</hi> (in Ezekiel) ravening the prey,<note place="margin">Ezek. 22.27.</note> he would have as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the <hi>life of his enimies;</hi> that ſo, leading his battles with victory, he might have enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged his Dominions by buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Townes with <hi>Blood</hi> and eſtabliſhing his Cities by <hi>Jniquity.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> (&amp; nothing but that) would have thought either of theſe things deſirable: but <hi>Solomon</hi> was of another temper; ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming more at the <hi>promoting of God's glory</hi> then the <hi>ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a carnall deſire;</hi> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, conſidering that he was made the <hi>Head</hi> of a great People, he deſired nothing ſo
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21739:7"/> much as <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> that hee might judge aright between them: <hi>Thy ſervant,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is in the midst of thy People, which thou haſt choſen; give therefore thy Servant an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding heart to judge thy People,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kings 3.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>that I may diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Good and Bad.</hi> V. 8.9.</p>
            <p>He, that rightly conſiders this petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> may well conceive, that <hi>Solomon</hi> had ſome <hi>wiſdome of heart,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he made it: and it was indeed a point of good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding (which too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny want) to be ſenſible, that, in reſpect of the place where in he was, hee wanted ſome Wiſdome, and accordingly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21739:7"/> to aske it. <hi>I am,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>a litle childe, and know not how to goe out or come in, therefore give me an underſtanding heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein he ſo far pleaſed <hi>God</hi> to his own advantage, that he ſoon received what he prayed for, and more in abundance; for, becauſe hee asked not <hi>long life, nor Riches, nor the life of his Enemies, but underſtanding to diſcern judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> therefore did the Lord give him <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> which he asked; and <hi>Riches</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> which he asked not; &amp; both in ſo great a meaſure, that <hi>none, which were before him, nor any, that came after,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kings. 3.12.13.</note> 
               <hi>were ever like unto him.</hi> v. 12.13
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21739:8"/> What was here ſo freely <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed</hi> in the <hi>Generall,</hi> we find as fully <hi>performed</hi> in ſundry <hi>Particulars</hi> in this tenth Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, whereof my <hi>Text</hi> is a part; where, (beſides the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of his abundant <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> recorded from ver. 13. to 23.) wee have a ſpecification of his <hi>excellent Wiſdome</hi> in the <hi>unparallel'd ordering of his houſe,</hi> and the full <hi>anſwering</hi> of all the Queen of Sheba's Queſtions; from ver. 2. to 6. in both which (namely his <hi>Riches</hi> and <hi>Wiſdome) he excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all the Kings of the Earth. ver.</hi> 23. So that here wee ſee the condition of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was far better, then was that of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21739:8"/> the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> when S. <hi>Paul</hi> to their ſhame objected to them, that <hi>there was not a wiſe man amongst them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>no not one that was able to judge between his brethren.</hi> It is not to bee doubted, but that <hi>many wiſe men</hi> were here; at leaſt 'tis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, that <hi>One</hi> here was, who was inſteed of many, for <hi>Wiſdome</hi> beyond all the reſt, and able to teach them all; which made him ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, that the <hi>wiſeſt</hi> thought it no ſcorne, but <hi>All</hi> their happineſſe to bee taught and bettered by the <hi>Wiſdome</hi> that was in him: and for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe they all ſought him with diligence to receive in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21739:9"/> from him; for ſo we read in the Text, that <hi>All the Earth ſought to Solomon to heare his Wiſdome,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And to whom ſhould <hi>All the Earth</hi> ſeek to heare <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> but to Him, who was the <hi>Wiſeſt of all the Earth? à Sapiente convenit Sapientiam diſcere:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euripides.</note> ſaith one; he, that wil learne <hi>true Wiſdome,</hi> muſt not (as the <hi>ſelfe conceited</hi> doe, who make <hi>themſelves</hi> their own teachers) take a <hi>Foole</hi> for his Maſter; but <hi>One,</hi> that is able to teach that, which he deſires to learne; and ſo the choice of this <hi>All</hi> in the <hi>Text</hi> was very good &amp; right in ſeeking after <hi>Solomon</hi> to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21739:9"/> be taught by <hi>Him,</hi> eſpecially conſidering <hi>who</hi> it was, that had been <hi>Solomon's</hi> Teacher before, namely <hi>God himſelfe:</hi> for they ſought to heare that <hi>Wiſdome, which God had put in his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that in the <hi>Text</hi> wee have both the <hi>ſufficiency</hi> of the <hi>Teacher,</hi> and alſo the <hi>dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> of the <hi>Learner. Solomon</hi> enabled of <hi>God</hi> to teach, and <hi>All</hi> the reſt ſeeking him out to bee inſtructed by Him. Whoſoever will teach others aright, muſt firſt himſelfe be taught of God; and every man, that hopes to get under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and wiſdome, muſt ſeek it with diligence.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:21739:10"/>
            <p>The Parts then of the <hi>Text</hi> are generally two.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Solomon's</hi> great <hi>Worth,</hi> in theſe words. <hi>His Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which God had put in his heart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The <hi>Fame</hi> and <hi>Eſteeme</hi> of this worth, in theſe. <hi>All the Earth ſought to heare.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the firſt <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> are 3 parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.
<list>
                  <item>1. Wherein <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> worth conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. <hi>viz:</hi> in his <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Whence hee had this wiſdome. <hi>viz.</hi> from <hi>God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. Where he laid up &amp; kept this wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>viz: in his Heart.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21739:10"/>
            <p>The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerall</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordeth likewiſe 3. parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.
<list>
                  <item>1. The <hi>Perſons,</hi> that ſo farre eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Solomon,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in this <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle. All the Earth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The <hi>Action,</hi> whereby they ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted this their eſteem, &amp; that was their <hi>Seeking,</hi> to him. <hi>They ſought.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The <hi>End</hi> of this ſeeking, &amp; that was to <hi>Heare him.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt <hi>God made Solomon Wiſe in Heart,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Generall </seg>1</label> and then <hi>All the Earth ſought to heare Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Of <hi>Solomon's Wiſdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſpeak of <hi>Wiſdome</hi> in the Audience of <hi>Fooles,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Paaticu∣lar. </seg>1</label> who
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21739:11"/> neither <hi>love</hi> nor <hi>know</hi> it, were to caſt <hi>pearles</hi> before <hi>Swine,</hi> which uſually ſtick not to trample the moſt pretious <hi>Iewels</hi> under their feet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they never knew what belonged to them: but in <hi>Athens,</hi> a Nurſery of wiſe men (where the generall profeſsion is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>love</hi> and <hi>ſtudy of Wiſdome</hi>) There to ſpeak of <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> is no leſſe proper, then tis for <hi>Athenians</hi> to ſtudy and practiſe it: nor is there any doubt to bee made of an anſwearable fruit; for, ſaith <hi>Solomon, give inſtruction to a wiſe man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 9.9.</note> 
               <hi>and he will be yet wiſer,</hi> Prov. 9.9. Jt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21739:11"/> will therefore be ſeaſonable to ſpeak of <hi>Wiſdome</hi> unto <hi>You</hi> as unto <hi>Wiſe men;</hi> and (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> once ſpake unto the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians) judge you, what J ſhall ſay;</hi> and the Lord give you underſtanding in thoſe few things, which for the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction</hi> of <hi>ſome,</hi> and the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancing</hi> of the <hi>reſt,</hi> ſhall now be ſpoken on this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of <hi>Wiſdome.</hi> Where firſt we are to enquire after that, which is not expreſſed, but only preſuppoſed in the <hi>Text,</hi> namely, <hi>VVherein true VViſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome doth conſist?</hi> And this we ſhall the better knowe, if firſt we conſider, <hi>what that is,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21739:12"/> wherein true wiſdome conſiſteth not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here, to make a full En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry, and anſwear it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, I might call in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more <hi>Particulars,</hi> than one houre would give mee leave to name; there being nothing indeed, which our <hi>owne Thoughts</hi> of themſelves (as we are Men) project; or this <hi>VVorld</hi> of it ſelfe ſuggeſteth to them, but may bee well brought into the number of thoſe things, wherein true Wiſdome conſiſteth not.<note place="margin">Sen. Epiſt. 125. Edit Baſil. 1590 vel Epiſt. 124. edit. Genev. 1626.</note> Wherefore <hi>Seneca</hi> in his 125: <hi>Epiſt.</hi> (where hee treats of <hi>this very ſubject</hi>) ſhall by a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21739:12"/> few <hi>Queſtions</hi> of his anſwer mine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid vires corporis exerces?</hi> Doſt thou ſtand (ſaith hee) on thy <hi>strength,</hi> and conceiue it a point of <hi>wiſdome</hi> to ſhew thy ſelfe more <hi>luſty</hi> &amp; <hi>ſtrong</hi> then others are? Suppoſe I doe ſo? Then, <hi>feris majores conceſsit natura:</hi> the <hi>wild Beaſts</hi> of the Forreſt would in this reſpect bee wiſer, becauſe ſtronger than <hi>Thou;</hi> and, if thou boaſt of thy <hi>ſwiftneſſe of foot, par lepuſculo non eris,</hi> the leaſt trembling <hi>Hare</hi> in the field, if thou have none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther help but thine own, will be wiſe enough to out-run
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21739:13"/> thee quite and leave <hi>Thee,</hi> as a foole, behinde.</p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>Quid formam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colis?</hi> Doſt thou eſteem it a peece of <hi>wiſdome,</hi> to mende, what <hi>God</hi> hath done, <hi>by pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out a cleerer beauty</hi> than firſt he gave thee, as did once that <hi>(Honeſt)</hi> woman <hi>Ieze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kings 9.30.</note> 2. Kings. 9.30? Suppoſe I doe this too? Then, <hi>Cum om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia feceris, à multis animalibus decôre vinceris:</hi> doe what thou canſt, and thou ſhalt ſee to thy ſhame (which, were it not for thy <hi>dawbing,</hi> would make thee bluſh) that ſome <hi>ſilly Birds</hi> will ſhew more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of ſplendour in the <hi>Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21739:13"/> of their hinder Parts,</hi> than thou canſt with all thy <hi>painting</hi> in the <hi>beſt</hi> of thy <hi>Face.</hi> Againe, <hi>Quid capillum ingenti diligentiâ comis?</hi> Doſt thou indeed think it <hi>wiſdome</hi> to ſpend ſometime in the <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ordering of thy haire?</hi> It was wont to be the ſaying of a reverent Divine, that <hi>he,</hi>
               <note place="margin">D.H.</note> 
               <hi>which hath too much regard to his Haire, hath commonly but li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle wit in his Head.</hi> But <hi>Seneca</hi> will anſwear his own que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion well enough; <hi>Cùm illum vel effuderis more Parthorum, vel Germanorum modo vinxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, &amp;c.</hi> When thou haſt, ſaith he, ſpread it abroad in the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21739:14"/> moſt glorious manner that may be, or laid it in as curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous knots, as all thy wit is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to contrive; <hi>In quolibet Equo denſior jactabitur juba, horrebit in Leonum cervice formoſior;</hi> when all is done, thou mai'ſt behold a <hi>Lion</hi> in this reſpect more <hi>glorious</hi> &amp; <hi>terrible</hi> to look on than <hi>thy ſelfe;</hi> and thy <hi>Horſe,</hi> whereon thou rideſt, will, in ſpite of all thy <hi>Art,</hi> carry a fairer <hi>Mane</hi> than <hi>Thou,</hi> and that which better becomes him.</p>
            <p>If in theſe things there bee litle <hi>wiſdome</hi> to be found, then give thy heart (as <hi>Solomon</hi> once did) to ſeek and ſearch
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21739:14"/> out all the <hi>works, that are done under Heaven,</hi> whither of <hi>Pleaſure</hi> or <hi>Profit,</hi> or of <hi>what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever condition</hi> they be; and if thou canſt finde true <hi>wiſdome</hi> in the contrivance of <hi>any one</hi> of them, fix thy heart <hi>There:</hi> onely bee ſure thou take not every thing for <hi>Gold</hi> that <hi>gli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters;</hi> but firſt bring it to the <hi>Touch-ſtone,</hi> to prove whither it be true or not;<note place="margin">Salvian. ad Eccleſ. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol. l. 3. p. 466. Edit. Oxon. 1629.</note> and therein <hi>Salvian</hi> will direct thee in a few words to very good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. <hi>Sapientia in exitu, &amp;c. VViſdome,</hi> ſaith he, is tried in the <hi>Concluſion; non in Pueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ, &amp;c.</hi> not in <hi>Childhood,</hi> not in <hi>Youth,</hi> not in <hi>Proſperity;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21739:15"/> 
               <hi>Quicquid in his lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, incertum eſt;</hi> a man knowes not what to make choice of in any one of theſe, as deſerving well the praiſe of <hi>wiſdome;</hi> there being in the <hi>Firſt</hi> too much <hi>weakneſſe,</hi> in the <hi>ſecond</hi> too much <hi>Raſhnes,</hi> in the <hi>Laſt</hi> too much <hi>Forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of God;</hi> in <hi>All</hi> too much <hi>Folly,</hi> and ſo, litle <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> in the <hi>Beſt</hi> of them: but in <hi>Exitu ſapientia;</hi> true wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is to fix on <hi>That</hi> alone which will hold out to the <hi>End.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider then of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thy <hi>Heart</hi> deſires, or thy <hi>Phanſy</hi> projecteth; whither
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21739:15"/> it be <hi>wallowing in pleaſures,</hi> or <hi>Tumbling in Gold,</hi> or <hi>Throw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down Others to rayſe Thy ſelfe,</hi> or <hi>Building up thine own Houſe upon other's Ruines,</hi> or the <hi>Enlarging of a Sonn's or Daughters portion by dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the Patrimony of Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Children committed to thy truſt,</hi> with any ſuch like fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhionable peeces of <hi>worldly wiſdome;</hi> conſider them all, &amp; ſeriouſly ask thine own ſoul, whither, in very deed or no, theſe things are like to ſtand thee in any ſtead on thy <hi>Death bed,</hi> when thy <hi>Conſcience</hi> (whither thou like it or no) ſhall call thee to an account;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21739:16"/> and thy <hi>Soul</hi> (whither thou wilt or not) muſt be reſigned up to the <hi>Diſpoſall</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> who gave it. If thou canſt be ſure, that theſe things (or any ſuch like) will <hi>Then</hi> ſticke cloſe unto thee, not to <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi> but to <hi>Eaſe</hi> and <hi>Comfort</hi> thee; then <hi>rejoyce in thy youth,</hi> or <hi>feed on gold,</hi> or <hi>ſupplant,</hi> or doe <hi>whatſoever</hi> thy heart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in; goe <hi>which way thou wilt,</hi> thou art in a <hi>right way</hi> of <hi>wiſdome;</hi> for common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>all is well</hi> that <hi>ends well.</hi> But if thou ſuſpect, that theſe things will <hi>then fayle</hi> thee, &amp; inſteed of <hi>Comfort</hi> be a <hi>Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> to thee (as it is much to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21739:16"/> be feared they will doe ſo) then be perſwaded to feare too, that there is ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable <hi>Folly</hi> in them; for doubtleſſe whatſoever will not hold out to help bring us <hi>Home</hi> to our God in Heaven, the proſequution thereof can never be true <hi>wiſdome</hi> in our <hi>Iourney</hi> while wee are on Earth.</p>
            <p>We ſee then what that is, <hi>wherein true wiſdome conſiſteth not,</hi> even all the <hi>VVaies</hi> and <hi>Projects of the world,</hi> which will not help us out <hi>in Exitu,</hi> when wee are to leave <hi>This</hi> World, and goe to <hi>Another;</hi> for that is the <hi>Touch-ſtone,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:21739:17"/> wherewith to try them all, whither they be pure <hi>Gold</hi> or <hi>Droſse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It would now bee worth our enquiry, to finde out what that is, <hi>wherein true wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome doth conſist indeed;</hi> for <hi>nullo modo magis prodeſſe poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi> in his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Epiſtle</hi>) there cannot be a more beneficiall imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then to ſhew what is <hi>true wiſdome,</hi> whereby we are differenced from all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther viſible <hi>Creatures,</hi> and come neere to the <hi>Creator,</hi> who is <hi>Wiſdome it ſelfe:</hi> and for this purpoſe, if thou wilt ſaith hee (leaving all thoſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21739:17"/> things, wherein other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe excell thee) if thou wilt <hi>ad bonum reverti tuum,</hi> look home and fix thy thoughts on <hi>That,</hi> which is proper to thy <hi>ſelfe</hi> as being <hi>Man;</hi> then briefly it is, <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus purus ac emendatus, aemu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lator Dei: true Wiſdome</hi> is, that with ſingleneſſe of heart we ſtrive to be, as far as it is poſsible to be, like unto the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Wiſdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And, what is required un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>This,</hi> we may collect from the ſeverall Particulars, wherin was expreſſed and made knowne that <hi>great wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> that made
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21739:18"/> him ſo famous.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Abulenſis in Textum.</note>Whither <hi>Solomon</hi> (as <hi>Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſis</hi> propoſeth the <hi>Query,</hi> and ſome have conceited of him) had the <hi>Wiſdome</hi> or <hi>skill</hi> to finde out all the hidden treaſures of the Earth, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came thereby ſo abundantly rich aboue other men, is a <hi>Queſtion</hi> both groundleſſe &amp; impertinent to our preſent purpoſe; for we finde, that as many as came to heare the <hi>Wiſdome</hi> of <hi>Solomon</hi> brought large gifts in their hands: the <hi>Queen</hi> of <hi>Sheba Talents of gold, Spices in abundance, and pretious ſtones.</hi> v. 10. and all the reſt brought, every man,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21739:18"/> 
               <hi>his veſſels of gold and ſilver, &amp; Garments, and Spices,</hi> with ſuch like more; and of <hi>Theſe a rate yeare by yeare.</hi> v. 25. and ſo it ſhould ſeem they were all <hi>rich</hi> enough before they ſought to <hi>Solomon;</hi> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 'tis unlikely they came with ſo much <hi>coſt</hi> and <hi>paines</hi> to heare this <hi>enriching wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of him. But, had <hi>this</hi> been their ayme, yet were all <hi>this,</hi> litle or nothing to the ſaving Wiſdome, that we are to ſeek for. Take then but a ſhort view of thoſe things, which are not far from my <hi>Text,</hi> and you ſhall ſee that <hi>Solomon</hi> was famous for his
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21739:19"/> 
               <hi>Wiſdome</hi> in matters (as wee are to eſteem them) of far greater worth and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: and theſe were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially foure.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His great variety of <hi>Songs</hi> and <hi>Proverbs,</hi> whereof <hi>Thoſe were a thouſand and five,</hi> and <hi>Theſe three thouſand.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">1. Kings 4.32.</note> Kings 4.32. and herein was ſeen his <hi>Inventing wiſdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. His <hi>ſpeeches</hi> concerning the nature of <hi>Beasts,</hi> and <hi>Foules,</hi> and <hi>Fiſhes,</hi> and <hi>Trees</hi> of all ſorts without excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;<note place="margin">V. 33.</note> and therein was manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted his <hi>Diſcourſing wiſdome:</hi> and for the fame of theſe things there <hi>came many to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21739:19"/> heare the wiſdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">V. 34.</note> 
               <hi>that was in him.</hi> v. 34.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His <hi>Anſwearing</hi> the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> to all her Queſtions; which were <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigmata,</hi> Riddles, Queſtions very hard to be reſolved; ſuch wherewith ſhe came to <hi>proue Solomon,</hi> or try his ſufficiency. 1. Kings, 10.1.<note place="margin">1. Kings 10.1.</note> to all which he gave her ſo full ſatisfaction, that <hi>there was not any thing hid from the King, which Hee told her not.</hi> v. 3.<note place="margin">V. 3.</note> and ſhee thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was ſo much taken with admiration of him, that the <hi>Text</hi> ſaies, <hi>there was no more ſpirit in her.</hi> v. 5.<note place="margin">V. 5.</note> and this was his <hi>Reſolving Wiſdome<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> a gift
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21739:20"/> of <hi>ſatisfying</hi> all thoſe who came with doubts unto him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. His admirable <hi>Deciding</hi> of the controverſie betwixt the two Harlots.<note place="margin">1. Kings 3.28.</note> 1. Kings 3. whereupon all <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as it is ſaid in the Text, <hi>feared the King, when they ſaw that the wiſdome of God was in him to doe judgement.</hi> v. 28. and this was his <hi>Rectifying</hi> and <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling wiſdome;</hi> a Wiſdome to ſet in order thoſe things, that were amiſſe, and ſo to rule &amp; governe aright.</p>
            <p>In the three former wee have <hi>Solomon's</hi> great <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> in this latter his ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Integrity</hi> and <hi>uprightneſſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21739:20"/> of heart;</hi> in both his <hi>compleat wiſdome;</hi> being wiſe to <hi>Know,</hi> and Wiſe to <hi>Doe:</hi> to <hi>Know</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very work that is done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun; for thereto hee <hi>gave his Heart.</hi> Eccleſ. 8.9.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.9.</note> &amp; of them all to <hi>Doe</hi> onely that, which is juſt and right; for that hee profeſſed to be his care when hee prayed for wiſdome, 1. Kings, 3.9.<note place="margin">1. Kings 3.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>So that now (if the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Solomon,</hi> the wiſeſt of all men upon Earth, may be our <hi>Patterne</hi>) we need go no further to learne what true <hi>wiſdome</hi> is; it being no other but <hi>That,</hi> which hitherto we have ſeen as a <hi>gift of God</hi> in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21739:21"/> 
               <hi>Solomon,</hi> namely, a true <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to ſee</hi> what wee are to doe, and a <hi>faithfull care to Doe</hi> what we ſee.</p>
            <p>This was the wiſdome, which <hi>Solomon</hi> prayed for &amp; obtain'd of <hi>God,</hi> and that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the counſell of <hi>David</hi> his Father; who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had commended this Wiſdome to him, as we may ſee,<note place="margin">1. Chron. 28.9.</note> 1. Chron. 28. <hi>And thou So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, my Sonne, know thou the God of thy Father, and ſerve him with a perfect heart,</hi> v. 9. as if he had ſaid, 'tis not likely thou ſhouldſt ever <hi>ſerve God</hi> with a perfect heart, except thou <hi>Know</hi> him firſt; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21739:21"/> 
               <hi>Know</hi> the <hi>God</hi> of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and 'twill bee to litle purpoſe <hi>to Know God,</hi> unleſſe thou <hi>ſerve</hi> him too; therefore <hi>Know God</hi> and <hi>ſerve him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What <hi>David</hi> here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, <hi>Solomon</hi> took care of; the <hi>One</hi> pointed out the right Way to be truly Wiſe, and the <hi>Other</hi> accordingly walked in it: and ſo from the <hi>Counſell</hi> of <hi>David</hi> the Father, and the <hi>Effect</hi> of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell in <hi>Solomon</hi> the Son, wee may ſee that <hi>True wiſdome is</hi> (above all other things in the world) <hi>to Know the God whom we are to ſerve, and accordingly to ſerve the God whom we know.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:21739:22"/>
            <p>Here I might enter on that uſefull Common-place of <hi>Speculative</hi> and <hi>Practicall wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;</hi> of the <hi>Knowledge,</hi> that we are all to ſeek for, and of the <hi>Practiſe</hi> that ſhould an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer this <hi>Knowledge,</hi> when we have it; and then I might ſhew in the <hi>former</hi> of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Neceſsity</hi> of <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> it being <hi>That</hi> eſpecially, which differenceth <hi>Man</hi> from other Creatures and <hi>Wiſemen</hi> from <hi>Fooles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The right <hi>Object</hi> of <hi>Knowledge;</hi> and that is Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing, which may help to bring us to the apprehenſion of God; but eſpecially <hi>God
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21739:22"/> himſelfe,</hi> who alone is the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable proper Object of all true Knowledge.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The true <hi>End</hi> of <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> and that is, not to ſet up our reſt in fruitleſſe thoughts and aery ſpeculations, but to <hi>Know</hi> that we may <hi>Doe;</hi> and this would bring in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of our <hi>Practicall wiſdome;</hi> the ſumme whereof <hi>Salvian</hi> giveth us in this ſhort but full expreſsion; <hi>ſapientia Chriſtiani eſt timor &amp; amor Chriſti:</hi> the true wiſdome of a Chriſtian (ſaith he, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of that wiſdome, which is <hi>Practicall</hi>) is to feare and love Chriſt, whoſe name we beare.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:21739:23"/>
            <p>This again I might point out more diſtinctly by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Bernards</hi> methode the <hi>Beginning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard. in Feſt. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreae. Serm. <hi>1.</hi> Edit. Pariſ. <hi>1632.</hi> Colum. <hi>325.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Progreſſe,</hi> and the <hi>Perfection</hi> of this <hi>Wiſdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Beginning</hi> of it (as <hi>Solomon</hi> directeth us, Prov. 1.7.<note place="margin">Prov. 17.</note>) is the <hi>Feare of the Lord,</hi> for with <hi>That</hi> we muſt begin, if ever wee will bee wiſe; and <hi>a good underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding have all they that doe thereafter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 111.10.</note> Pſal. 111.10. and as many as lay not true <hi>Religion</hi> the <hi>Feare of the Lord</hi> for their Foundation, may bee ſure they ſhall prove themſelves very <hi>Fools</hi> in the concluſion.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:21739:23"/>2. That the <hi>Progreſſe</hi> or <hi>Continuation</hi> thereof is in <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Expectation to gird up the loynes of our minde and to hope to the end,</hi> as S. <hi>Peter</hi> doth put us in remembrance 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.13.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.13</note> and ſo to <hi>run with patience the race that is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage us. Heb. 12.1.<note place="margin">Heb. 12.1.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 That the <hi>Perfection</hi> of it is <hi>Charity;</hi> which (according to the ſame <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> Col. 3.14.<note place="margin">Col. 3.14.</note>) <hi>is the bond of all perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> a true <hi>Charity</hi> unto <hi>Men,</hi> who beare in them the ſame Image of <hi>God</hi> with us, and that for the teſtifying of our true <hi>Love</hi> unto <hi>God himſelfe,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:21739:24"/> whoſe Image both <hi>They</hi> and <hi>We</hi> doe beare: and doubtleſſe that <hi>Practiſe,</hi> which begins with <hi>Gods feare,</hi> and goeth on with <hi>Hope and confidence</hi> in him, reaching full home to a true <hi>love of God and Man,</hi> even <hi>That</hi> is a perfect <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe,</hi> and a true <hi>Practicall wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> if there bee any that is true.</p>
            <p>The <hi>End</hi> and <hi>Crowne</hi> of which <hi>Wiſdome</hi> is the full fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ition at laſt of the <hi>Preſence</hi> of that <hi>God,</hi> whom here by our wiſdome we have ſeen <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, through a glaſſe, and knowne in part,</hi> but hereafter (as the perfection of our Wiſdome)
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21739:24"/> wee <hi>ſhall ſee him face to face,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.12.</note> 
               <hi>and know him as we are knowne.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. Of this <hi>Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive wiſdome</hi> in the <hi>neceſſity,</hi> right <hi>Object,</hi> and true <hi>End</hi> thereof; and of <hi>this Practicall</hi> in the <hi>Beginning, Progreſſe, Perfection,</hi> and <hi>Crowne</hi> of it, J might well ſpeake more as of Mans <hi>trueſt wiſdome</hi> and happineſſe; but of this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject I have here ſpoken more at large heretofore upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Text:</hi>
               <note place="margin">On 1. Cor. 15.34.</note> and of the necesſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of joyning them both (viz. <hi>Speculation</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi>) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeake ſomething againe in the 2. <hi>Generall,</hi> where wee
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21739:25"/> are to be put in minde of <hi>ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> them both. Jn the meane time, that we may know of whom to obtaine, when we ſeeke them, it will bee requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite that in the next place we take notice, <hi>whoſe Gift</hi> they are and that is, <hi>Gods alone;</hi> which is the next <hi>Particular</hi> of the <hi>Text.</hi> viz. Whence <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> had his great wiſdome even from <hi>God himſelfe.</hi> For all ſought to heare his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, not which he had fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of his own Phanſie, but <hi>which God had put in his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Particular. </seg>2</label> Which God had put in his heart.</p>
            <p>And who is hee, that can
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21739:25"/> put true wiſdome into the heart of Man, but <hi>God</hi> who alone is truly wiſe? <hi>Jf any one of you lacke wiſdome,</hi> ſaith S. James, <hi>let him aske it of God. James</hi> 1.5.<note place="margin">Iam. 1.5.</note> Where the Apoſtle doth clearely intimate, not only with what confidence wee may aske and hope for <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> when we aske it of <hi>Him;</hi> but alſo how litle hope there is to obtaine, when we aske it of any <hi>Other</hi> but of <hi>Him</hi> alone.</p>
            <p>If it bee <hi>Speculative Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> which conſiſteth in <hi>Knowing</hi> the right, it is God alone that gives it; for 'tis <hi>He</hi> (and only He) <hi>that teacheth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21739:26"/> man knowledge.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 94.10.</note> Pſal. 94.10. and his ſpirit is therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>ſpirit of Knowledge.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 11.2.</note> Iſai. 11.2.</p>
            <p>Or, if it be <hi>Practicall Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> which is the <hi>Doing</hi> of what we know; even <hi>That</hi> is the Gift of <hi>God</hi> alone too.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Beginning</hi> of it, which is the <hi>Feare</hi> of God, is from none but Himſelfe. I (ſaith the Lord) <hi>will put my Feare in their hearts.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 32.40.</note> Ierem. 32.40. And doubtleſſe if <hi>He</hi> never put it there, wee ſhall there never finde it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Progreſſe</hi> or <hi>Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation</hi> of it, which is <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Truſt</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> even <hi>This</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:21739:26"/> alſo is from <hi>Him</hi> alone. <hi>The God of Hope</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Fill you with Joy and Peace in beleeving that you may abound in hope.</hi> Rom. 15.13.<note place="margin">Rom. 15.13.</note> And ſurely if <hi>He</hi> doe not fill us with Ioy and Peace, wee ſhall be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether empty and hopeleſſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Laſtly the <hi>Perfection</hi> of this <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> which is the true <hi>Love of God and Man,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>This</hi> too is only from the <hi>God</hi> of love; it being the <hi>fruit of his ſpirit,</hi> Galat. 5.22.<note place="margin">Gal. 5.22.</note> And queſtionleſſe did not this <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God</hi> incline our hearts to love <hi>God</hi> for his <hi>Own</hi> ſake, and <hi>Men</hi> for <hi>His,</hi> wee ſhould quickly have litle true <hi>Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21739:27"/> either to <hi>Man</hi> or <hi>God;</hi> but rather indeed whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>God</hi> and good <hi>Men</hi> hate, that ſhould we love.</p>
            <p>Whither it be then <hi>Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative</hi> or <hi>Practicall,</hi> a <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> or <hi>Doing Wiſdome,</hi> it is what God alone that gives it: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Whom,</hi> if once we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of our <hi>ſelves</hi> to be wiſe, we ſhall prove in the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as very Fooles, as did that <hi>Father</hi> and <hi>Son</hi> (which <hi>Bonaventure</hi> out of S. <hi>Hierom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bonavent. D. Sal. c. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> ſpeakes of) who fondly went about to empt the Sea with a litle ſpoone; which 'tis like they might as eaſily have done, as we can of our
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21739:27"/> ſelves alone ſound the <hi>Depth of wiſdome without God,</hi> who gives it; the <hi>One</hi> as likely and eaſie to bee done as is the <hi>Other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if you will know what becomes of Men, when <hi>here</hi> they adventure to leave <hi>God</hi> and to goe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him, then <hi>Solomon</hi> (who found it by experience) will tell you. Eccleſ. 7.29.<note place="margin">Eccl. 7.29</note> namely that <hi>God,</hi> for his part, <hi>hath made man upright, but they have found out many Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> and that is by leaving God, who made them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right: and here to ſhew you the manifold <hi>Inventions,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:21739:28"/> which men by leaving God in their <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> doe unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily finde out and run into, were to lead you with my ſelfe into a <hi>Labyrinth</hi> of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny crooked waies and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finde a way to get out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Philoſophers</hi> of <hi>Old,</hi> and the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> of <hi>latter times</hi> will abundantly ſhew us, what <hi>Jnventions</hi> there may be in the <hi>ſpeculative</hi> part of Wiſdomes; Both of them, I confeſſe, in their kind labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and excellent too for many <hi>Rules</hi> &amp; <hi>Precepts</hi> wel deſerving the ſtudious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry of the ſoundeſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21739:28"/> but, wee know, the beſt unwinnowed <hi>Wheat</hi> is mixed with <hi>Chaffe,</hi> and <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of</hi> there hath been found ſo much in <hi>Theirs,</hi> that (if the fruſtrating, or at leaſtwiſe the hazarding of many good Endeavours be not diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled) there is need of a ſtrong breath to blow it away. the groundleſſe <hi>Dreames,</hi> and <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions</hi> of the <hi>One,</hi> and the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious perplexing <hi>Niceties</hi> of the <hi>Other</hi> having ſo far mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted their Readers &amp; diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted their intentive thoughts from the <hi>Truth,</hi> which they look't for, that it is now one part of a Wiſe man indeed to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21739:29"/> diſcern aright between the <hi>Wheat,</hi> and the <hi>Chaffe;</hi> the <hi>Streame</hi> and the <hi>Froth;</hi> the Rules of <hi>wiſdome,</hi> which they pretend to give, and the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe <hi>Inventions</hi> which they have put us upon. So that notwithſtanding in many things they have done the World very good ſervice (as indeed they have) yet in <hi>This</hi> reſpect wee may ſay of them (as <hi>Elibu</hi> did once of <hi>Job) that they haue opened their mouth in vaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 35.16</note> 
               <hi>and multiplied words without knowledge,</hi> or (which is all one) they have magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied themſelves in a great deale of ſpeculative know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21739:29"/> to very litle purpoſe; &amp; all becauſe, truſting to the perfection of their own <hi>wit</hi> &amp; <hi>Iudgement,</hi> they ran, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God, into many <hi>Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of their <hi>Own:</hi> and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe did not we ſometimes after <hi>Their</hi> example gather up <hi>Droſſe</hi> for <hi>Gold</hi> and fill our thoughts with <hi>Aery ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> of very litle conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence (as too often we doe) we ſhould many of us be <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer</hi> than we are; and it would be well wee did remember, that in <hi>this</hi> regard wee are wiſe but in our <hi>Own conceits;</hi> for then <hi>Solomon</hi> would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially tell us. Prov. 26.12.<note place="margin">Prov. 26. i2</note>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:21739:30"/> that <hi>there is more hope of Fools than of ſuch wiſe men</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Should I now ſhew you the <hi>Inventive wiſdome</hi> of Men (without God) in that part, which is <hi>Practicall,</hi> I might then tell you of the <hi>Rich man</hi> in the Goſpell; who, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring long with himſelf what he ſhould doe, had found out a way at laſt (by enlarging his Barnes) to be merry for <hi>Many</hi> yeares; and that was a dainty plot and a point of good <hi>wiſdome</hi> indeed, if it had not fayl'd him; but we finde in the <hi>Text</hi> that he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Foole</hi> for his labour; and he got ſo litle by that <hi>Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:21739:30"/> that in the very firſt night, which came over his head, he loſt his <hi>Soule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.20.</note> Luk. 12.20. Or, I might tell you of <hi>Achitophel</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> two great <hi>Polititians</hi> in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall times; the <hi>One</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray his Soveraigne <hi>David</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Other</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Redeemer</hi> of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> and therein 'tis likely they ſuppoſed themſelves the wiſeſt of all their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. But this was a new <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention</hi> of their own, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God was not with them; and, to prove the goodneſſe thereof, <hi>God</hi> ſuffred the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell</hi> to adde one <hi>Invention</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:21739:31"/> more, and that was, to <hi>finde</hi> out a way, the <hi>One</hi> to ſet his houſe in Order, the <hi>Other</hi> to reſtore the price of blood, &amp; <hi>Both</hi> to hang themſelves; whih was at once the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Concluſion</hi> of all their <hi>wiſdome.</hi> Such commonly is the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of thoſe men, who ſtudy <hi>Themſelves;</hi> and ſuch for the moſt part are all thoſe <hi>Inventions,</hi> which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver came from God, <hi>That</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone being true wiſdome which we are taught of <hi>Him;</hi> and whatſoever <hi>He</hi> teacheth us, we need not doubt of the truth thereof; and happy are they whom <hi>God</hi> ſhall pleaſe
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21739:31"/> to teach. But now as it is with the <hi>Word of God,</hi> which is the <hi>Rule,</hi> whereby we are taught all true <hi>wiſdome:</hi> ſo is it alſo with our <hi>wiſdome,</hi> which we are taught there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. <hi>That,</hi> namely the Word of God, ſometimes enters in at the <hi>One</hi> eare and paſſeth out at the <hi>Other,</hi> making no ſtay at all, becauſe it never had any good entertainment in the <hi>Affections</hi> within: and <hi>This,</hi> namely our <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> is no ſooner gotten but as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily ſometimes loſt againe, becauſe it was never <hi>There</hi> treaſured up where it ſhould be kept; and where <hi>That</hi> is
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21739:32"/> to be done, is (next unto the <hi>Getting</hi> of it) the moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable point in our <hi>wiſdome.</hi> The <hi>Text</hi> referreth us for this purpoſe unto the <hi>Heart</hi> of Man; for tis ſaid here that the <hi>wiſdome,</hi> which made <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> ſo famous, was that <hi>which God had put in his Heart,</hi> and <hi>There Hee laid it up and kept it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Particular. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Which God had put into his Heart.</hi> (that is, which he had fully poſſeſt his underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with, and whereunto he had alſo inclined his <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> to lay hold on, and delight in it; for <hi>That</hi> is indeed to have Wiſdome in
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21739:32"/> the <hi>Heart,</hi> even throughly to <hi>Know</hi> and heartily to <hi>Imbrace</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> it: and doubtleſſe, if ever we think to keep and uſe this gift with <hi>Content</hi> to our ſelves or <hi>benefit</hi> to others, we muſt <hi>There,</hi> in the <hi>Heart,</hi> treaſure up the <hi>wiſdome,</hi> which God doth give unto us. Wherefore, when <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> perſwadeth his <hi>Son</hi> (that is every obedient Learner) to receive inſtruction, hee bids him to give him his <hi>Heart</hi> too. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.26.<note place="margin">Prov. 23.26.</note> to devote his <hi>Affections</hi> unto <hi>wiſdome,</hi> and to ſet his beſt <hi>Love</hi> upon it; which we muſt doe, if ever we will be truly <hi>wiſe</hi> or <hi>True
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21739:33"/> in Heart:</hi> for of this <hi>Duty</hi> there is a double neceſsitie; the <hi>One</hi> in reſpect of the <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> which wee deſire to have, and the <hi>Other</hi> in regard of our <hi>Heart,</hi> wherein we are to keep it.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of our Wiſdome this <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Applying the Heart</hi> is needfull; both to the <hi>getting</hi> of our <hi>wiſdome,</hi> and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the <hi>Perfection</hi> of it, when we have gotten it.</p>
            <p>Needfull it is to the <hi>Get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> of our <hi>wiſdome,</hi> becauſe, without <hi>Applying the Heart,</hi> we may daily receive Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of <hi>wiſdome,</hi> and yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be truly wiſe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21739:33"/> 
               <hi>Solomon</hi> commends <hi>this</hi> for the right way to find out the knowledge of God. <hi>If thou wilt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>receive my words and incline thy Eare, and apply thy Heart to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, then ſhalt thou finde out the knowledge of God.</hi> Prov. 2.2.5.<note place="margin">Prov. 2.2.5.</note> The <hi>Receiving of words</hi> &amp; the <hi>inclining of the eare</hi> are meanes of ſingular conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; yet to finde out the Knowledge of God (which is the ſumme of all true <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>) they are to very litle purpoſe of themſelves alone without <hi>Applying the Heart</hi> thereunto: but with <hi>This</hi> we may finde out and bring to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21739:34"/> paſſe any thing, that wee are capable of; as we may ſee in the example of <hi>Solomon,</hi> who confeſſeth to our Inſtruction that when hee <hi>Applied his Heart to know wiſdome, hee then beheld all the work of God.</hi> Ecc. 8.16.<note place="margin">Eccl. 8.16.</note> and till <hi>then</hi> 'twas not poſsible that ever hee ſhould behold it.</p>
            <p>Againe, this applying of the Heart is needfull (as to the <hi>getting</hi> ſo) to the <hi>Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of our <hi>Wiſdome</hi> when we have gotten it; the beſt of our <hi>wiſdome</hi> (if not ſetled in the <hi>Heart</hi>) being no better than the <hi>Fooliſhneſſe of Fools, which is</hi> very <hi>Folly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 14.24.</note> Prov. 14.24.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:21739:34"/>
            <p>For be it a <hi>Speculative,</hi> or <hi>Knowing wiſdome,</hi> which we have obtained and boaſt of as of our glory; if it be not fixed in the <hi>Heart</hi> but reſt in the <hi>Tongue,</hi> it is a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erball</hi> ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, a very <hi>Froth</hi> of Wit and nothing elſe. Or, be it a <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cticall</hi> or <hi>Doing wiſdome,</hi> which we have got the plot of and ſtand upon as our greateſt Policy; if <hi>this</hi> too be not ſetled in the <hi>Heart,</hi> but onely appeare in outward <hi>ſhewes,</hi> it is but a <hi>Forme of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe without the Power there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,</hi> a meer <hi>Hypocriſie.</hi> Both <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>Practiſe,</hi> if they reach not to the <hi>Heart,</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:21739:35"/> are but as ſeed that is caſt on the <hi>Face</hi> of the Earth, which the Foules of the Aire will ſoon ſteal away, and leave the Husbandman in a vaine expectation of an harveſt, that wil never come.<note place="margin">Hoſea 10.12.</note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth us to <hi>Break</hi> up the ground of our <hi>Hearts;</hi> to <hi>lay open</hi> our <hi>Hearts</hi> as wide, as we can, for the receiving of <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> that ſo the Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thereof may ſink <hi>Downe</hi> and take root in the <hi>Depth,</hi> and thence ſpring forth and become fruitfull and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table at the laſt. In reſpect then both of the <hi>Getting</hi> and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21739:35"/> alſo of the <hi>Perfection</hi> of our <hi>wiſdome,</hi> this <hi>Applying of the Heart</hi> is a Duty of needfull conſequence. There is alſo a neceſsity hereof in reſpect of the <hi>Heart it ſelfe;</hi> which, ſaith Ieremie, <hi>is deceitfull aboue all things, Ierem.</hi> 17.9.<note place="margin">Ierem. 17.9.</note> and who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he be, though never ſo exact a <hi>Phariſee,</hi> that think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not ſo of <hi>His heart,</hi> is much deceived in his <hi>Heart;</hi> and 'tis indeed the very cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of <hi>his heart,</hi> which hath blinded &amp; ſo deceived him, and will daily deceive him more, making him to <hi>be yet more vile than thus;</hi> and openly to appeare, as hee is, a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21739:36"/> very <hi>Foole,</hi> even then when he looks to bee accounted <hi>wiſe.</hi> But if <hi>wiſdome</hi> bee once planted in this <hi>deceitful heart</hi> of Men, it will ſoon remove the <hi>Deceit,</hi> &amp; make the <hi>heart</hi> to become faithfull to <hi>God</hi> &amp; true to <hi>Man:</hi> for, <hi>when wiſdome entreth into thy heart, Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is pleaſant to thy ſoule, then Diſcretion ſhall preſerve thee, understanding ſhall keepe thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 2.10.11.</note> Prov. 2.10.11. Poſſeſſe thy <hi>heart</hi> then with true and ſound <hi>wiſdome,</hi> and thy <hi>heart</hi> which before was <hi>deceitfull,</hi> ſhall never fayle thee.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſumme</hi> then of this Part is; that, as wee aske all
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21739:36"/> our <hi>wiſdome</hi> of <hi>God</hi> alone, ſo with the <hi>Heart</hi> wee ſhould imbrace &amp; love the <hi>wiſdome,</hi> which he beſtoweth on us: and <hi>This</hi> indeed is the way to make the <hi>wiſdome,</hi> that he giveth us, to be truly <hi>Ours;</hi> for ſo we finde it was with <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> of whom it is ſaid in the <hi>Text,</hi> that <hi>All</hi> came to heare <hi>His wiſdome.</hi> It was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed originally the <hi>wiſdome of God,</hi> becauſe HE gave it, and yet it was <hi>Solomons own wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> too; for <hi>God</hi> had put it into <hi>Solomon's heart,</hi> where he had full poſſeſsion of it.</p>
            <p>It is the abundant <hi>Riches</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> that hee hath at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21739:37"/> 
               <hi>wiſdome</hi> and all other <hi>Gifts</hi> to bleſſe us with, of whoſe fulneſſe every man receives whatſoever hee is bleſt withall; and 'tis alſo the free <hi>Bounty</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> when hee gives them to us, to lay aſide as it were the <hi>Propriety</hi> of them, making them to <hi>Be</hi> and letting them to be <hi>Called Our Wiſdome,</hi> and <hi>Our Gifts,</hi> and <hi>Himſelfe</hi> in them <hi>our God</hi> too; and that is when <hi>He</hi> and his <hi>Gifts</hi> have taken up our <hi>Heart;</hi> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we have no right to nor part in either <hi>Him</hi> or <hi>Them;</hi> but when they are <hi>There,</hi> in the <hi>Heart,</hi> then are
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21739:37"/> 
               <hi>they</hi> all <hi>Ours</hi> and We are <hi>His: His Wiſdome</hi> is <hi>Ours</hi> to make us acceptable, <hi>Himſelfe Ours</hi> to make us happy; &amp; We are <hi>His,</hi> both <hi>For</hi> our <hi>Wiſdome</hi> to be thankfull unto him, and by our <hi>wiſdome</hi> to make him known to others as farre as we our ſelves doe knowe him.</p>
            <p>For this purpoſe, when God once planteth the <hi>Tree</hi> of <hi>wiſdome</hi> in the <hi>Heart</hi> of Man, his <hi>Bleſsing</hi> uſually ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the <hi>Fruit</hi> thereof to look over the Wall and be <hi>Seen</hi> abroad, and by it's <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> to draw many with <hi>Deſire</hi> and <hi>Admiration</hi> to it: for ſo
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21739:38"/> we finde in <hi>Solomon</hi> here in my <hi>Text;</hi> namely, that <hi>when</hi> God had once made him wiſe in <hi>Heart,</hi> he was <hi>then</hi> daily ſought to, as a Man who had God with him whither ſoever he went; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one thinking himſelfe happy to gather ſome of the <hi>Fruits</hi> that flouriſhed in his Garden, to learn ſome of the <hi>VViſdome</hi> which <hi>God</hi> in ſo great a meaſure had given to Him; and this brings in the ſecond <hi>Generall</hi> part of the <hi>Text,</hi> viz. The Fame and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of <hi>Solomon's</hi> Worth.</p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Generall. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>All the Earth ſought to Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon: &amp;c.</hi> It is ſeldome ſeen
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21739:38"/> that true worth paſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way without ſome <hi>Eſteeme</hi> and <hi>Acceptance,</hi> unleſſe it bee amongſt thoſe who are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ignorant or unworthy of it; for <hi>Ita comparatum eſt in rebus humanis,</hi> ſaith one,<note place="margin">M. Piccar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus obſerv. Dec. 3. c. 7.</note> 
               <hi>ut vel in viti virtutem excellentem admiremur;</hi> It is the uſuall condition of Man, that where there is any <hi>Worth</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> in the Beholder, there is commonly ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective <hi>Admiration</hi> of the <hi>Excellency</hi> that he beholds in other Men. Let <hi>Homer</hi> (though never ſo blinde) ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe in his <hi>Art</hi> the Reſt of his time, and whole Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21739:39"/> will bee at odds about him to lay clayme to him &amp; call for him as their Own; which might well occaſion that of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb. Ep l. 6. Ep. 42.</note> 
               <hi>Sapientis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria Mundus eſt;</hi> and, <hi>Sapiens ubi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> civis eſt:</hi> that a wiſe man is a creature of ſuch conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who <hi>By</hi> his <hi>Wiſdome</hi> knows how to make uſe of all places aright, as if he were ſtill at home, and whom <hi>For</hi> his <hi>Wiſdome</hi> all places will readily accept, as if they had ſome title &amp; intereſt in him: there being ſuch an attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Excellency in <hi>Wiſdome</hi> (as <hi>Tully</hi> ſpeakes) as that,<note place="margin">Tul. 2. de Fin. p. 108. edit. Hanov 1609.</note> 
               <hi>Si oculis videretur, quàm illa ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21739:39"/> amores excitaret ſui?</hi> if it could be ſeen with an Eye of fleſh, the moſt carnall man, that ever was, would be drawn to look after <hi>It</hi> with a love and deſire whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he would or no.</p>
            <p>Great without queſtion is the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of <hi>That Wiſe God,</hi> whoſe <hi>Gift of wiſdome</hi> in a common expreſsion of it was ſo much adored, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Chriſtians, but even by thoſe men, who never had the true knowledge of God himſelfe: and <hi>Groſſe</hi> and <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid,</hi> more <hi>Fleſhly</hi> than <hi>They,</hi> muſt we needs be thought to be, if we think it not our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21739:40"/> to become truly <hi>wiſe,</hi> when all the world before us hath been ſo much tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the admiration of <hi>Wiſdome.</hi> Let it be the porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Aſſe</hi> to carry a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Gold,</hi> which he knows not the worth of; it is <hi>His</hi> portion, and let <hi>Him</hi> beare it; but, if <hi>Balaam</hi> be a <hi>Foole,</hi> that rides upon him, the <hi>Aſſe</hi> may chance to ſpeak as much to the purpoſe as <hi>Hee;</hi> for, the <hi>Aſſe</hi> and the <hi>Foole</hi> are both alike.</p>
            <p>To prevent this, as I have in the firſt <hi>Generall</hi> ſhewed what true wiſdome is, ſo let me now briefly put you in
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21739:40"/> mind of ſeeking after it, and that by the example of <hi>All the Earth,</hi> which (as it is in the Text) ſought to <hi>Solomon</hi> to heare, &amp;c. Where <hi>firſt</hi> wee have conſiderable Who <hi>They</hi> were, that ſo far eſteemed <hi>Solomon</hi> for his Worth; and they are expreſſed in this Particle, <hi>All the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is; <hi>Generally,</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Particular. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>all the Inhabitants of the Earth;</hi> or more <hi>Eſpecially All the Kings of the Earth;</hi> for ſo this <hi>All</hi> is limited. 2. Chro. 9.23;<note place="margin">2. Chron. 9.23.</note> where the ſame <hi>Text</hi> is repeated.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All the Kings</hi> ſought, &amp;c. When <hi>Kings</hi> ſeek after <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> tis likely the Gift of <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:21739:41"/> is <hi>Glorious</hi> &amp; <hi>Deſirable;</hi> ſo it is, and beſt of all others, befitting <hi>Them;</hi> none having ſo much need of <hi>wiſdome</hi> as <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Rulers;</hi> for <hi>This,</hi> if in any <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of the Earth, is in <hi>Them</hi> eſpecially <hi>the principall thing;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (according to the adviſe of <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſeſt of all <hi>Kings) They</hi> of all Others ſhould ſtrive <hi>with all their get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to get underſtanding:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 4.7.</note> to get a <hi>Speculative</hi> or <hi>Knowing wiſdome</hi> to Diſcern between Good and Evill, and alſo a <hi>Practicall</hi> or <hi>Doing wiſdome</hi> to be Exemplary in Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Both</hi> to <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:21739:41"/> aright: and <hi>This</hi> for <hi>Kings</hi> to deſire and ſeek after will be in <hi>Them</hi> (as it was in theſe here in the <hi>Text</hi>) an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of their <hi>Humility,</hi> of a due acknowledgement, that they Rule and Governe by the guidance of a <hi>King</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, <hi>by whom alone all Kings doe raigne and Princes decree juſtice,</hi> Prov. 8.15.<note place="margin">Prov. 8.15.</note> and 'twill be a manifeſtation of their <hi>Fidelity</hi> and <hi>Care</hi> too; that, in ſeeking after <hi>Wiſdome</hi> (as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> did) to goe in and out aright, their deſire is to be in the performance of their <hi>Charge</hi> faithfull unto God, who hath call'd them to it.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:21739:42"/>
            <p>But I ſtand not here now to read a Lecture of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome unto <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours:</hi> It is our happineſſe, that we (of all parts of the World) have cauſe enough to bleſſe God for crowning the <hi>Throne</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome</hi> with the <hi>wiſdome of Solomon</hi> theſe many yeares to this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day; where <hi>All,</hi> that ſtand before it (and <hi>Some</hi> to their ſhame) may behold a <hi>Sear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching wiſdome of God</hi> in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aright, with an <hi>Exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Integrity</hi> well befitting the Imitation of the very beſt <hi>And let it be thy good pleaſures O Lord, for the continual main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21739:42"/> of thy Truth, and the advancing of thine own Glory in this our Kingdome, thy cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Iſrael, to double this Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly wiſdome of the</hi> FATHER <hi>upon the</hi> SONNE <hi>to many gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again (to follow the <hi>Text</hi> in the full extent of the Words) <hi>All the Earth</hi> ſought to <hi>Solomon,</hi> that is, <hi>All ſorts of men upon Earth</hi> without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. And who, of <hi>All men,</hi> without exception, is there that needs not ſeek to finde out Wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e? As for <hi>Knowledge</hi> the <hi>Speculative</hi> part thereof, it is not good the Soule ſhould be without it. Pr. 19.2.<note place="margin">Prov. 19.2.</note> becauſe <hi>This</hi> muſt guid us in the way
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:21739:43"/> wherein we go,<note place="margin">Iſai. 33.6.</note> &amp; ſo wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting <hi>This</hi> we goe without a guid, &amp; run headlong (to our own deſtruction) wee know not into what.<note place="margin">Hoſea, 4.6.</note> Now if any had of <hi>This</hi> enough of his own, he need not then ſeek out for more. bu S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> will tell us, that the World, <hi>Sapientiâ ſuâ,</hi> by it's own <hi>wiſdome</hi> knew not God.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.21.</note> 1. Cor. 1.21. nor is there any hope it ſhould ever know him, if it have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>Wiſdome</hi> then it's <hi>Own</hi> and therefore, as Wee are Men of the <hi>World</hi> (and the <hi>Beſt</hi> are no better of <hi>Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi>) we muſt <hi>All</hi> ſeek out beyond our <hi>ſelves</hi> for <hi>that Knowledge and VViſdome,</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:21739:43"/> which He giveth unto Men to know him with.</p>
            <p>But, did wee abound in <hi>This,</hi> yet are we not truly wiſe, as long as we fall ſhort in that part which is Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call; which to <hi>All men,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception, is needfull, to make them appeare worthy of the vocation, wherewith they are called, whereunto S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſo earneſtly exhorteth Epheſ. 4.1.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 4.1.</note> Jn the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance whereof as long as we fayle, our <hi>Knowledge</hi> (though never ſo great) is but that <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> which in <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis volat</hi> (as S. Gregory ſpeaks in his Morals) like a painted
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21739:44"/> feather toſt in the Ayre, and vaniſhing away wee know not how; or it is <hi>cibus indige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> (as S. <hi>Bernard</hi> compares it) like to meat undigeſted,<note place="margin">Bernard. in Cant. Serm. <hi>36.</hi> circa. med.</note> which may chance to bring a ſurfeit in the end: Whence <hi>Tully</hi> doth not unfitly call true <hi>Wiſdome Ars vivendi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tul. l. <hi>1.</hi> de Fin p. <hi>82.</hi>
               </note> a certain Art of Living Well; This being indeed <hi>The Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> that muſt keep alive &amp; preſerve both our <hi>Knowledge</hi> and our <hi>Selves.</hi> Wherein how far Men of themſelves fall ſhort, when they truſt to their own ſtrength and ſeek no further, wee may learne from the experience of <hi>Judas</hi>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:21739:44"/> (before mentioned) with many more, who (ſuppoſing themſelves to bee none of this All in the Text, that are to ſeek for Wiſdome) have runne themſelves along through their own Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to an End far worſe then ever their <hi>Beginning</hi> was.</p>
            <p>We (Beloved) are of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men (if Any be) in a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed way of <hi>All</hi> kinde of <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome;</hi> of <hi>Knowledge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Conſider, and the Lord giue you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding in all things. <hi>2. Tim. 2.7.</hi>
               </note> which in every corner profereth it ſelfe unto us. <hi>God</hi> knowes how much or how litle we think we need it; and of <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> which in many <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies</hi> is made good before us;
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:21739:45"/> 
               <hi>God</hi> knowes too how much or how litle we are carefull to follow it. It will be, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion, a <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery</hi> too, if the ſimple <hi>vulgar,</hi> who <hi>Know</hi> leſſe than we but in plaine honeſty <hi>Practice</hi> more; if <hi>Theſe,</hi> I ſay, doe one day riſe up in judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us and condemne us for that, which we <hi>Know</hi> &amp; <hi>Practice</hi> not. From this <hi>ſhame</hi> and <hi>miſery</hi> good Lord deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Vs:</hi> And ſure we may be, that, if ever wee think to anſwer the bountifull Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of God towards us, it is onely true <hi>Wiſdome</hi> muſt make us fit to doe it: &amp; <hi>This</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:21739:45"/> if we deſire to find and have, we muſt <hi>ſeek</hi> it out; which is the <hi>Action,</hi> whereby this (ALL) expreſſed their eſteem of <hi>Solomon's</hi> worth. <hi>They ſought</hi> unto him.</p>
            <p>There is a double vanity, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Particular. </seg>2</label> which too many are poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with; and that is, on the <hi>One</hi> ſide to ſeek that which is not worth the <hi>finding;</hi> and on the <hi>Other</hi> to neglect that which is wel worth the <hi>ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king:</hi> each of them is a folly, &amp; he, which is guilty of the <hi>One,</hi> is ſeldome free from the <hi>Other.</hi> The way to avoid <hi>Both</hi> is (with this, <hi>All,</hi> in the <hi>Text</hi>) to ſeek for <hi>Wiſdome;</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:21739:46"/> which muſt be <hi>ſought</hi> for, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of it ſelfe it will never come unto us; and it is well <hi>worth</hi> the <hi>ſeeking,</hi> becauſe it is pretious. <hi>One ſmall peece</hi> of ſilver (in the 15. of <hi>Luke</hi>) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the lighting of a can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to finde it out: be it never ſo litle, yet, if it be <hi>Silver,</hi> it is worth the looking after; much more; if it be <hi>Gold</hi> or <hi>Pretious ſtones;</hi> and <hi>Wiſdome</hi> indeed is all <hi>Theſe</hi> and more. <hi>How much better is it?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 16.16.</note> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) that is, 'tis far bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>to get wiſdome than Gold, &amp; to get underſtanding rather to be choſen then ſilver;</hi> for when we talke of <hi>That,</hi> wee then
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21739:46"/> ſpeak of <hi>Silver</hi> and <hi>Gold</hi> and all the <hi>Treaſures</hi> of the World caſt together; All which we may have and be rich there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, if we doe but ſeek it: For, <hi>if thou ſeekeſt Her as ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and ſearcheſt for her as for hid Treaſures, then ſhalt thou underſtand;</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> who found it ſo Prov. 2.4.5.<note place="margin">Prov. 2.4.5.</note> Where, calling it a <hi>Treaſure,</hi> he ſheweth how well it <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves;</hi> &amp;, in ſaying it is <hi>Hid,</hi> he putteth us in minde how much it <hi>requires</hi> our <hi>ſeeking:</hi> which two are <hi>Motives</hi> to perſwade us to the ſeeking of it; and Motives ſufficient they are (except it be to a
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:21739:47"/> ſelfe-conceited <hi>Foole</hi>) to put anyman with diligence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
            <p>But here the materiall <hi>Queſtion</hi> will bee, <hi>when</hi> and <hi>where</hi> and <hi>how</hi> we are to ſeek it?</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>When?</hi> The <hi>Son</hi> perhaps would gladly put it off till his Pleaſures be ended, and the <hi>Father</hi> untill his Projects be contrived, both ſuppoſing the Gravity of <hi>wiſdome</hi> better befitting the <hi>Grandfathers</hi> yeares. So in deed too many doe, and die Fooles for their labour; for (ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccleſ. 9.10.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.10.</note>) <hi>there is neither Knowledge nor wiſdome in the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:21739:47"/> grave whither thou goeſt;</hi> and then it is much to be feared that <hi>They,</hi> which never had any before, will finde but li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle when they are going <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the grave. Wee ſhould then ſet upon it with our might in the <hi>Morning</hi> of our Age, as <hi>ſoone</hi> as wee can, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we know not how <hi>ſoone</hi> we ſhall goe; as ſoone, as poſsibly wee can, wee ſhould ſeek &amp; ſtrive to <hi>know God</hi> and <hi>ſerve</hi> him.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If in the next place you aske me <hi>where</hi> wee may ſeek and finde this <hi>wiſdome,</hi> I will then anſwer, that you muſt not think to find much good
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:21739:48"/> water, but either in the <hi>ſtreames,</hi> or at the <hi>ſpring-head;</hi> and <hi>There,</hi> at the <hi>Head,</hi> you ſhall be ſure to finde it clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt. <hi>Wiſdome</hi> is that <hi>water</hi> of life, which the <hi>Lord</hi> by the <hi>Prophet</hi> inviteth every man to come freely unto,<note place="margin">Iſai 55.1.</note> Iſai, 55.1. The <hi>Head-ſpring</hi> of this Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is a <hi>VVell</hi> of <hi>Gods own</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, namely, his ſacred <hi>word;</hi> about which (unleſſe wee chance to meet (as too many doe) with ſome invidious <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> that will lock it up from us, we need have no <hi>Contention</hi> now; as the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> often had about their <hi>VVells;</hi> for God hath now
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:21739:48"/> made it freely <hi>Ours,</hi> &amp; every man may come and draw without exception, and yet never empt it, becauſe it is an <hi>Everlasting ſpring.</hi> The <hi>ſtreames</hi> of <hi>wiſdome,</hi> flowing from this <hi>Head,</hi> are thence gone out into all the <hi>world,</hi> which never had ſo many <hi>Helps</hi> for <hi>wiſdome,</hi> as <hi>Now</hi> it hath ſo that, goe <hi>where</hi> you will if you ſeek for <hi>wiſdome,</hi> it will be very hard if you find it not. Only you may chance in your way to meet with ſome <hi>Ditches</hi> of <hi>Puddle,</hi> fit for none but <hi>Aſſes</hi> to drink in; which the <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Friers</hi> with ſuch like <hi>wiſemen</hi> have
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:21739:49"/> digged for us, purpoſely to ſtay us from looking after better Waters; ſetting us on work with ſome <hi>Tales</hi> and <hi>Fables</hi> of their <hi>Own</hi> to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold us from the <hi>word</hi> of God &amp; as many good <hi>Books,</hi> as poſsibly they can. When <hi>Theſe</hi> or any ſuch wee meet with (as often we doe) wee need not make any long ſtay at them; or, if we doe ſo, we ſhall bee very litle the better for them. But, goe to the <hi>Spring,</hi> the <hi>word of God;</hi> or any <hi>streames,</hi> which proceed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>That;</hi> and <hi>There</hi> you ſhall be ſure to finde true <hi>wiſdome,</hi> if you ſeek it <hi>Aright.</hi> Which is
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:21739:49"/> the next <hi>Query,</hi> namely, <hi>How we</hi> are to ſeek it.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Hovv? And <hi>How</hi> ſhould we ſeek wiſdome in the <hi>word of God,</hi> but only by daily <hi>Reading</hi> &amp; <hi>Meditating</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in? Which I forbeare any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to commend to <hi>You,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is <hi>Your Profeſsion;</hi> &amp; I hope it is Your <hi>Practice</hi> too. Yet thus much let mee put <hi>You</hi> in minde of (which too many forget) that, as the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of <hi>Samaria</hi> ſaid once to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Well is deep,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>and We of our ſelves, have nothing to draw withall:</hi> All our <hi>Reading</hi> and <hi>Meditation</hi> will but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex and trouble us, if <hi>God</hi>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:21739:50"/> doe not proſper us with a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> on it. It is ſaid of theſe Men here in the <hi>Text;</hi> that when they ſought to <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> they brought <hi>Preſents</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gifts</hi> with them,<note place="margin">1 Kings 10.25.</note> with them, v. 25. and ſo muſt we ſeek unto the <hi>God of Solomon;</hi> with the <hi>Gift of Praiſe</hi> for what we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; with the <hi>Gift and Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crifice of Prayer</hi> for what we want, and <hi>this</hi> is the way to ſeek and finde the <hi>Gift of Wis<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome,</hi> which we deſire. Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> therefore thou takeſt thy <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble</hi> or any other <hi>good Book</hi> in thy hand to ſeek <hi>Wiſdome</hi> in it, ſay, with <hi>David, Lord open thou mine eyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.18.</note> 
               <hi>that I may ſee
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:21739:50"/> the wonderous works of thy Law;</hi> and then thou needeſt not doubt, but thou ſhalt behold the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of <hi>Wiſdome</hi> to thy great content; eſpecially, if (as <hi>Solomon</hi> his Son gives the adviſe Prov. 4.20.<note place="margin">Prov. 4.20.</note>) thou <hi>attend to his Words,</hi> and not ſeek to mend what hee hath done, but <hi>humbly incline thine Eare to hearken what hee ſhall ſay.</hi> And herein Theſe <hi>Seekers</hi> in the <hi>Text</hi> may be a fit <hi>Patterne</hi> to us; for <hi>They</hi> ſought to <hi>Solomon,</hi> not to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove</hi> and <hi>Correct</hi> him, but to <hi>Heare</hi> and be Inſtructed by him; which brings in the laſt <hi>Part</hi> of the <hi>Text,</hi> namely
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:21739:51"/> the <hi>End</hi> of their ſeeking, and that was to <hi>Heare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Particular. </seg>3</label> They came to <hi>Heare Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon;</hi> and that preſuppoſeth that <hi>Solomon,</hi> though a <hi>King,</hi> was ready and willing to <hi>Teach</hi> them; otherwiſe hee had been no fit <hi>Type</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who (though a greater than <hi>Solomon</hi>) did litle elſe but <hi>Teach;</hi> and among other <hi>leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> that he taught, he taught this <hi>One</hi> to his Own Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; namely that they ſhould goe out and <hi>Teach all Nations.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28.19</note> Which <hi>Precept</hi> of <hi>His,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his own <hi>Example,</hi> wrought ſo much with them, that neither <hi>Tumults</hi>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:21739:51"/> nor <hi>Priſons,</hi> neither <hi>wicked Men</hi> nor <hi>Divells</hi> could ſtop them from it; but, caſting out the <hi>One</hi> and confuting the <hi>Other,</hi> they went on to <hi>Teach</hi> in ſpight of <hi>All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And who the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is <hi>He,</hi> that is too good to <hi>Teach? Seneca,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sen. Ep. <hi>90.</hi> alias <hi>89.</hi>
               </note> in his 90. <hi>Ep.</hi> will tell us, that a wiſe man is but <hi>Humani ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris Poedagogus;</hi> by his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</hi> a <hi>Schoolmaſter,</hi> a <hi>Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> to any man that will learne of him. The Sonne of <hi>Syrach,</hi> Ecclus, 21.13.<note place="margin">Ecclus, 21.13.</note> will tell us; that the <hi>Knowledge of a wiſe man ſhall abound like a flood;</hi> and that is, not onely to be full up to the <hi>bancks,</hi> but
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:21739:52"/> ſometimes to <hi>Run over</hi> &amp; wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Fields that are about it. <hi>Solomon</hi> alſo, Prov. 15.7. will tell us,<note place="margin">Prov. 15.7.</note> that the <hi>Lips of the wiſe diſperſe knowledge, but the heart of the fooliſh doth not ſo.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the <hi>Hebritians</hi> will tell us, that one &amp; the ſame word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies not only to <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand,</hi> but alſo to <hi>Inſtruct;</hi> to ſhew that he, which hath knowledge, muſt not hide it, but <hi>Teach</hi> therewith: yea, the ſame word ſignifieth alſo to <hi>Proſper,</hi> to have good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe; to put us in minde for our encouragement that He, which is carefull to <hi>Teach</hi> according to the wiſdome
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:21739:52"/> that he hath, is in a way to doe good not only to <hi>Others,</hi> but alſo to <hi>Himſelfe</hi> too; for <hi>God</hi> doth commonly follow with a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> and <hi>Proſper</hi> thoſe, who diligently goe <hi>That</hi> way to work. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Saint <hi>Paul</hi> will exhort us, Col. 3.16.<note place="margin">Col. 3.16.</note> that the <hi>Word of Chriſt dwell in us plentifully in all wiſdome, teaching and admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing;</hi> and laſtly the <hi>Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of Solomon</hi> will (Eccleſ. 12.9.<note place="margin">Eccle. 12.9.</note>) aſſure us too; that, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was wiſe, he Taught the People Knowledge;</hi> or, (as it is in the Margine) the more wiſe he was, the more hee <hi>Taught</hi> the People. It is then
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:21739:53"/> a property of <hi>wiſdome,</hi> that by our <hi>wiſdome</hi> wee ſtrive to make others wiſe; and 'tis a point of no great wiſdome to cenſure the Endeavours of <hi>Other</hi> men, and in the meane time doe litle good with our <hi>Own:</hi> This only by the way ſhould bee remembred, that none <hi>Teach</hi> where they are not call'd, nor before they are able; nor make <hi>One</hi> kinde of <hi>Teaching</hi> a let and hindrance to <hi>Another:</hi> but they, which can <hi>(pro ratione Loci &amp; Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonae)</hi> one way or other ſhould <hi>Teach;</hi> and for this Work there is <hi>None</hi> too good. But <hi>Teaching</hi> of Wiſdome
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:21739:53"/> wil be to litle purpoſe, except there be ſome to <hi>Heare</hi> and learne vvhat is <hi>Taught;</hi> and therefore, as it is preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Text, there vvas a <hi>Solomon</hi> to <hi>Teach;</hi> ſo 'tis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaid too, there came many to <hi>Heare.</hi> And indeed, to be ready to <hi>Heare,</hi> is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry end of our ſeeking &amp; the vvay to finde out vviſdome. Wherefore vvhen <hi>Solomon</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired <hi>God</hi> to give him an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and vviſe heart, he uſed a vvord,<note place="margin">1. Kings 3.9.</note> which (in the <hi>Originall</hi>) ſignifies <hi>Cor au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diens,</hi> an <hi>Hearing</hi> heart, as it is expreſt in the Margine; to ſhew, that how underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:21739:54"/> and vviſe ſoever a man be, he muſt alwaies be ready to <hi>Heare,</hi> that ſo he may un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand more and be Wiſer ſtill: and ſo vvill every one, that is not a Foole, doe; for, ſaith <hi>Solomon, give Inſtruction to a wiſe Man and Hee will bee yet wiſer;</hi> becauſe hee will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ready to <hi>Heare,</hi> which is the vvay to be vviſer than he was before. <hi>Heare</hi> then vve muſt; and to <hi>Heare</hi> vvee muſt <hi>ſeek</hi> and <hi>run</hi> too, yet not beyond the <hi>Bounds</hi> that are ſet about us. When theſe men in the Text ſought to <hi>Heare,</hi> there was then but one <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in <hi>All</hi> the Earth; &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:21739:54"/> 
               <hi>All</hi> the Earth ſought to <hi>Solomon:</hi> but now, bleſſed be <hi>God, Christ</hi> (who vvas grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>He</hi>) hath made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Solomons</hi> inſteed of <hi>Him.</hi> Shall then a ſelfe-conceited <hi>Troup</hi> run to ſeek out <hi>Other Solomons</hi> of their own chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing abroad, becauſe (in the judgement of ſome) their <hi>Own</hi> at <hi>Home</hi> is not ſo Wiſe as <hi>they?</hi> though ſome doe ſo in ſimplicity of heart, being lead in a throng, and think no harme, yet of <hi>Other ſome</hi> it is to be feared, that, chuſing their <hi>Teachers,</hi> they will in time make choice of the <hi>leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> which they intend to
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:21739:55"/> learne too, and then we may know what to look for of them: A <hi>Parlour,</hi> an <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſticall Conventicle</hi> with a <hi>Cenſure</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> may chance to ſerve for a <hi>Temple,</hi> a <hi>Congregation</hi> and a <hi>Sermon. God</hi> deliver the Womb of this Church from that viperous <hi>Brood,</hi> which hath too long ſtruggled in Her.</p>
            <p>But, ſuppoſe the covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the <hi>Jmpropriator,</hi> or (which is worſe) of the <hi>non-reſiding Incumbent,</hi> who come only at the ſheep-ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; ſuppoſe that <hi>Theſe</hi> doe ſcarce leave enough behinde
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:21739:55"/> them to make a poor Curate ſpeak, except perhaps of his own wants, may wee not <hi>then</hi> ſeek out a <hi>Solomon</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to heare <hi>Him?</hi> That caſe indeed is miſerable and to be lamented. <hi>God</hi> in his mercy, for the ſaving of thoſe that are <hi>His,</hi> in due time free this Church from all <hi>thoſe,</hi> who thus make <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe</hi> of the <hi>Soules</hi> of Men;<note place="margin">Rev. 18.13.</note> and that by putting either better Solomons in <hi>Their</hi> roome, or better <hi>Hearts</hi> in Them.</p>
            <p>In the mean time unleſſe it can be ſhewed that <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> is better than <hi>Obedience,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.22.</note>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:21739:56"/> a Journey further will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be altogether excuſed: withall it ſhould be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred too, that there is <hi>None</hi> ſo low, but hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of <hi>God</hi> in him: of <hi>God,</hi> who knows how to bring <hi>Light</hi> out of <hi>Darkneſſe,</hi> and to manifeſt <hi>Strength</hi> in <hi>Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and by <hi>ſmall</hi> meanes to bring <hi>Mighty</hi> things to paſſe; and ſurely the Water or Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is never the worſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is brought in a <hi>Veſſell</hi> of <hi>Wood.</hi> It were a weakneſſe to be on the <hi>One</hi> ſide ſo eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly content, as not to care how litle we have; and it would be a <hi>Preſumption</hi> to
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:21739:56"/> be on the <hi>Other</hi> ſo wiſe in <hi>Owne</hi> Conceit, as to preſcribe unto <hi>God,</hi> what he ſhall doe for us. If therefore any thing be wanting in <hi>Others</hi> parts, doe thou ſupply that with thy earneſt <hi>Prayers</hi> &amp; daily <hi>Meditations,</hi> and the plaine <hi>Honesty</hi> of thine own Heart, for <hi>That</hi> indeed with a litle <hi>Teaching</hi> will be more to the purpoſe, and pleaſe <hi>God</hi> bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than a great deale of <hi>Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching,</hi> and litle <hi>Honeſty</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe there bee at <hi>Home</hi> a true <hi>Solomon</hi> indeed; then, I hope, we need goe no further to ſeek out more; and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:21739:57"/> who at home would not be ready and willing to <hi>Heare Him?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 14.18</note> Hee, which hath a peece of <hi>ground</hi> to bee <hi>ſeene,</hi> or an Yoke of <hi>Oxen</hi> to bee <hi>proved,</hi> or a <hi>Delilah</hi> to bee <hi>ſported</hi> with; or perhaps a <hi>ſelfe-conceit</hi> of doing as much good by <hi>Reading</hi> at the ſame time in his Cloſet; <hi>Theſe</hi> and ſuch like, though call'd for, would not be very willing to come, but rather deſire to bee excuſed; nay, 'tis much to bee feared they would have no great deſire to heare <hi>Solomon,</hi> though he ſhould ſeek after and come home to them.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:21739:57"/>
            <p>Of this <hi>Neglect</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> there might bee much ſaid to good purpoſe, and ſcarce enough: but in ſteed hereof I muſt ſhut up this &amp; conclude all; and that ſhall be with humble Prayer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Almighty <hi>God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">One of the Church prayers.</note> that hee will bee pleaſed to grant us knowledge and true under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of his Word; that, all Ignorance being expelled, we may know what his will and pleaſure is in all things, and how to doe our duties, and truly to walk in our vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations; and that we may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo expreſſe in our living
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:21739:58"/> thoſe things that wee doe know; that we be not onely Knowers of his Word, but alſo Workers of the ſame; which is the way to be truly Wiſe; <hi>And hereunto, O Lord, we beſeech Thee to incline our Eares, and open our Hearts to underſtand and imbrace what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever wee ſhall at any time Heare, that ſo wee may bee the more fit to glorifie Thee our God on Earth here, and the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prepared to reigne with</hi> THEE <hi>and our</hi> JESVS <hi>for ever in Heaven hereafter; and this we pray for, in the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</hi> JESVS CHRIST,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:21739:58"/> 
               <hi>To Whom with Thee, O Father and the Holy Ghoſt be all Glory and Honour now and for Ever,</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <trailer>Glory bee to GOD, Good will towards MEN.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21739:59"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
